distribute system

Mapreduce: simpilfied data processing on big cluster
	
	user generate a set of intermiediate key/values pair, and a reduce function that merge all intermidiate 
	values associated with same intermidiate key. this allow programmers without any experience with parallel 
	and distritubuted sytsem to utilize the distributed system.

	implementation:
	the procedure of map reduce function:
		1: the main mapreduce function separate the data into several parts, and start the map and reduce
		function. 
		2:the is one master function which assigned M map tasks and R reduce task. the master function
		assign the task to idle workers.
		3:the worker who is assigned map task read the input file. it pass the each k/v pair to map 
		function and buffered in the memory.
		4:the buffer pair write in the local disc, the location of those pair pass to master, which could
		be used by the reduce funtion.
		5:the reduce function read the buffer data from the local disks. it sort and group it together.
		if the data is too large the external sort is used.
		6:the reduce iterates over the sorted intermediate data and for each unique key, it pass the key
		to user's reduce funtion. the output would append to the final output. 
		7:return to the master

	input and output types:
	performance:
	1:search through one terabyte data and find a specific pattern.
	2:sort one terabyte data.

6.24 hashing 
	u-large set of all possible keys 
	v-small set of slots 
	hash table T[v] index by v
	a key A stored at hash table at slot s=h(a)
	h is a hash function from u to v
	every slot is a linked list
	collision two keys in the same slot

	dictionary implementation
		insert(a) check if a into the table, keep every key distinct,insert a into T[h(a)]
		search(a) search a T[h(a)] 
		delete(a) search and delete 

		run time 
		insert O(N)
		search O(N) worst case 
		delete O(N)

	how to avoid collision, use randomization
	we use a random seed R, h(R,a) to get the slot number, choose the random seed when I initialize the hashtable
	R is choose from a seed space {r1,r2,r3...}
	Note hr(a)=h(r,a)

	universal hashing 
	R-finite set of seeds 
	H = {hr}
	m=|s|
	defnition: H is called universal hashing, for a,b in universal keys, a!=b
	the chance of hr(a)=hr(b) less than (the total number of seeds)/(slots)

	suppose R is a random variable in seed space 
	probablity[hr(a)=hr(b)]<1/m
	implementation: suppose we implement hash table, if we perform a universal hashing 
	the number keys in table is o(m) m is the number of slots 
	the operation is constant 
	inner product hash let m=prime number 
	u=zm^t set of all t-tuples with entry in Zm
	seeds=zm^t
	slot=zm

6.30 hash
	hash function
	in java the hash code compute in a string A length t as 
	A[0]*31^(t-1)+A[1]*31^(t-2)+A[2]*31^(t-3)+A[4]*31^(t-5)+....+A[t-1]
	the use of hashmap in java 
	initialize: HashMap<obj,obj> map=new HashMap<obj,obj>();
	put: map.put(obj,obj);
	
	mapreduce hide many detail:
		sending map code to server 
		track with task are done 
		moving data from map to reduce 
		balance load over server 
		recover from failures 

7.2 mapreduce 
	design overview 
	assumption:
		the system is build from many inexpensive, so it often faliure. we need constantly monitor and detect,
		workload contains two kinds of reads:
		large streaming read and small random read 
	
	interface:
		we support the usual operations to create,delete,open,close,read and write files.
		GFS support that many client to append data to same file concurently. which is called snapshot 

	chunk size:
		we choose 64MB

	Metadata 
		three types of metadata
			the file and namespace
			the mapping from file to chunks
			the location of each chunks' replicas

	chunk location 
		the master did not keep persistent record of which chunk server have a replicate of give server.

7.3
	threads 
	have multiple threads
	I/O concurrency parallelism 
	event driven programming 
	between process there's no interaction 
	in the process there would be several thread, there will contacts in all these thread 
	Thread chanllenge:
	
	why go?
		go support for threads
		convienient RPC(remote process call)
		type safe 
		garbage-collected 

	thread 
		go calls gorountines 
		thread allows a program do many things at once 
		each thread excute serially, just like a non-thread program
		the threads share momory 
		each thread include per-thread state:	 program counter,register,stack
		the thread could express concurrency, which you need in distributed system
		I/O concurrency:
			client sends request to many server in parallel and wait for replies 
			server process multiple client requests: each requestion may block 
			while waiting for the disk to read data for client X, process a request for client Y.
		Multicore performance:
			excute code in parallel on several cores
		convenience 
			in backgroud, once per second,check whether each worker is still alive 
		
	Is there an alternative to threads?
		yes, in a single thread, write a code that interleaves activities.
		unusally called event driven 
		keep a table of state of each activity. 
		one "event driven table" like this:
			check new input for each activity
			does the new step for each activity,
			update state
		event driven get your I/O concurency:
			eliminates threads cost
			but it does not get muti-core speedup.
			and is painful for program.

		threading challenge
			share data:
			what if two thread do n=n+1 at the same time? or one read another one increment?
				 use lock 
				 avoid	sharing mutable data
		coordination between threads:
			one thread is producing data, another thread is consuming it.
			how can the consumer wait and realease the CPU?
			how can the producer wake up the consumer?
				use go channels or sync cond or waitgroup
			deadlock 
				cycles via lock and/or communication

7.6	use "go" key word could create a new thread, and continuely run the left program

7.7 go sharing and lock versus channels
	go package sync 
		high-level synchronization is better done via channel and communication 
	type cond 
		cond implimetation a condition variable,a rendezvous point for the occurence event 
	func NewCond(l Locker) *Cond
		NewCond returns a new Cond with Locker l.
	func (c *Cond) Broadcast()
		Broadcast wakes all goroutines waiting on c.
		It is allowed but not required for the caller to hold c.L during the call.
	func (c *Cond) Wait()
	type Locker
		A Locker represents an object that can be locked and unlocked.

		type Locker interface {
			Lock()
			Unlock()
		}
	type Mutex
		A Mutex is a mutual exclusion lock. The zero value for a Mutex is an unlocked mutex.

7.9 
	// MathUtil 用于数学计算
	type MathUtil struct {
	}

	// CaculateCircleArea 计算圆的面积
	func (m *MathUtil) CaculateCircleArea(req float64, resp *float64) error {
	    *resp = math.Pi * req * req
	    return nil
	}

	第一个参数req代表的是调用者（client）传递提供的参数。
	第二个参数resp代表要返回给调用者的计算结果，必须是指针类型。
		
	1.initial a struct, this struct worked as a meduim to pass the content between sever and client
	type name struct{}
	2.in the sever program, we need to register the type struct. with the following function 
	func (t *name) functionname(request t1, response *t2) error
	the first parameter request is provided by the client, the second is returned to the client and it must 
	be a pointer 
	normally this function return nil, if there's no error occur

	in the server program 
	1. name:=new(name)
	we first create the object
	2.we register the object to the rpc client 
	err:=rpc.Register(name)
	if(err!=nil){
		log.Panic(err)
		return 
	}
	3.
	rpc.handleHTTP()
	we subbit our stuff to	http, which means we could use http way to pass the data.
	4.
	listen,err:=net.listen("tcp",":8081")
	use a specific port to listen 
	if(err!=nil){
		panic(err.Error())
	}
	http.Serve(listen, nil)

	on the client we need first connect to the server 
	client,err:=rpc.DialHTTP("tcp","localhost")
	if err!=nil{
		panic(err.Error())
	}
	after we connect to the server, we could call it function 
	var req float64
	req=3;
	var resq *float64
	err=client.Call("MathUtil.CalculateCircleArea", req, &resp)

7.17
